<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>I like tight pants and mathematics</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/" />
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/feed/us/recent_entries.xml" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2010-05-27:/and//1</id>
    <updated>2011-10-30T22:53:49Z</updated>
    
    <generator uri="http://www.sixapart.com/movabletype/">Melody 1.0.0</generator>

<entry>
    <title>Albert Camus’ algorithm</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/albert-camus-his-algorithm" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2011:/and//1.31</id>

    <published>2011-10-30T21:58:50Z</published>
    <updated>2011-10-30T22:53:49Z</updated>

    <summary>swim, dry in the sun, rewrite the sentence, think really hard, rewrite the sentence, look at the beautiful boys and girls, rewrite the sentence</summary>
    <author>
        <name>jenseits</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<p><a href="/and/assets/called/zuid_superia_400_6_bij_6.jpg"><img src="/and/assets/scaled/to/830/wide/and/called/zuid_superia_400_6_bij_6.jpg" alt="You see a swimming pool in the south, lined with azaleas." title="" /></a></p>

<p>This is how I imagine Camus when I read his diary, and this seems like a good model for living: you go to a swimming pool in Algiers, swim, dry in the sun, look at the beautiful boys and girls, think really hard, look at the beautiful boys and girls, think really hard, write a sentence, rewrite the sentence, swim, dry in the sun, rewrite the sentence, think really hard, rewrite the sentence, look at the beautiful boys and girls, rewrite the sentence.</p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>The voice of the shell</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/the-voice-of-the-shell" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2011:/and//1.30</id>

    <published>2011-10-26T18:20:28Z</published>
    <updated>2011-10-26T22:44:54Z</updated>

    <summary>I am moved by the program telling me everything is ok. (…) In any case it’s endearing: I imagine the programmer as a pretty dark-haired boy. He is shy and his eyes that hide already behind large glasses avoid your gaze. And Igor is not so handy with words, but he means good with the world. </summary>
    <author>
        <name>tellyou</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<p>I tell my students that the command line is the way to go. I am not the kind of person who thinks the command-line is somehow a more true experience though—it’s another modality, another way of accessing and manipulating the data on your machine.</p>

<p>The query-response format is wonderful. I amaze students with the whoami command—the computer knows the answer! This gives the impression, to some, that the console allows you to have conversations with your computer.</p>

<p>I do often feel like I am talking to the computer. But when the computer talks balk to me, from time to time the voice of the computer gives way to the voice of the programmer who wrote it. Or at least, my image of this programmer. This is the output of a 7zip command:</p>

<pre>7-Zip  4.44 beta  Copyright © 1999-2007 Igor Pavlov  2007-01-20
p7zip Version 4.44 (locale=nl_NL.UTF-8,Utf16=on,HugeFiles=on,2 CPUs)

Processing archive: Fedora 9.7z

Extracting  Fedora 9/Fedora 9.vmkd
Extracting  Fedora 9/Fedora 9.nvram
Extracting  Fedora 9/users.txt
Extracting  Fedora 9/Fedora 9.vmx.lck/M00232.lck
Extracting  Fedora 9/Fedora 9.vmx
Extracting  Fedora 9/Fedora 9.vmxf
Extracting  Fedora 9/Fedora 9.vmsd
Extracting  Fedora 9/Fedora 9.vmx.lck
Extracting  Fedora 9

Everything is Ok</pre>

<p>I am moved by the program telling me everything is ok. I am not sure if Igor Pavlov meant to give me consolation from the console—after all, the sentence is logically equivalent to ‘there are no errors’. It could be a simple observation.</p>

<p>In any case it’s endearing: I imagine the programmer as a pretty dark-haired boy. He is shy and his eyes that hide already behind large glasses avoid your gaze. And Igor is not so handy with words, but he means good with the world. </p>

<p>But the encounter is not always so nice. The reason I install Fedora is because I have to compile some Perl modules to put on my shared hosting service to make Movable Type work (all of this takes place some time back). The interactive mode of CPAN has the most condescending error messages ever.</p>

<p>Yet nothing beats Telnet. When typing in RCPT: instead of the required RCPT TO: I get:</p>

<pre>Error: I can break rules, too. Goodbye.</pre>

<p>And my connection is closed. I feel like I can actually strangle the programmer responsible for this behaviour. The rude message is a catalyst for my negative passions. I imagine the programmer delighting in his sense of control over me and I want to smash the keyboard on his head.</p>

<p>I project in my mind this monster: crouched behind his computer, staring intently at the screen, a system administrator, overweight and unkempt hair, staring maniacally at the screen, laughing out loud about this error message that is going to upset the people using his code. But I have been awake too long. I made him in my own image; look at me: I’m also alone, staring maniacally at the screen, making up these stories about computer programmers.</p>

<p>With minds so volatile and temperaments so inflammable, it’s important we stay nice to each other. If the only way we talk to each other is through error messages, we better make these exceptionally kind.</p>


<div id="aside"><p>The shell is the text-based environment in which you give commands to your computer. Quite similar to the way the DOS operating system worked. On a contemporary Linux or Mac OS X system you have access to a fully functioning shell (Applications, Accesoires, Terminal).</p>

<p>This article was written for <a href="http://libregraphicsmag.com/" title="Libre Graphics Magazine">Libre Graphics Magazine</a>. A magazine dedicated to showcasing graphic design done with free and open source tools. <a href="http://libregraphicsmag.com/buy.html" title="Libre Graphics Magazine: now.">Buy</a>, <a href="http://libregraphicsmag.com/download.html" title="Libre Graphics Magazine">download</a>!</p>
</div>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>Physical Hyperlinks that Glitter</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/physical-hyperlinks-that-glitter" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2011:/and//1.29</id>

    <published>2011-09-22T14:11:40Z</published>
    <updated>2011-09-22T17:24:08Z</updated>

    <summary>I cut out 424 squares in sparkly adhesive and create the QR-code for the hyperlink to this very blog.</summary>
    <author>
        <name>baseline</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<style>
#content .grid_1 {
  color: #999;
}

#content .grid_1 a {
  color: #bbb;
}

#content .grid_1 h4.author {
  color: #000;
}


</style>

<p><img src="/and/assets/scaled/to/830/wide/and/called/physical_hyperlinks_that_glitter.jpg" alt="You see a white wall on which is constructed a QR-code. The squares that constitute the code are pink and glittery, made from some thick adhesive pasted to the wall." title="" style="width:830px;height:551px;"/></p>

<p class="byline">Photo by <a href="http://www.jhoeko.com/">Jhoeko</a></p>

<p>For the shared exhibition of our <a href="http://www.dedcr.nl">studio complex</a> I want to show current work. But most of what I do is for the screen now. So I make a physical hyperlink to the blogosphere. I cut out 424 squares in sparkly adhesive and create the QR-code for the hyperlink to this very blog. Not every phone manages to scan it correctly—I’m not sure if it’s because the grid is slightly crooked, or because the glitter is confusing.</p>

<p><img src="/and/assets/scaled/to/490/wide/and/called/try_glitter_link.jpg" style="width:490px;height:370px;" alt="You see a group of people in front of the glitter code, trying it out with their telephone"/></p>

<p class="byline">Floris Schönfeld gives a guided tour, visitors try to visit the glitterlink. Photo Eelco van der Lingen</p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>Learning how to program</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/learning-how-to-program" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2011:/and//1.28</id>

    <published>2011-08-11T09:04:34Z</published>
    <updated>2011-08-11T09:08:59Z</updated>

    <summary>I get the big blue book, and I start watching the screencasts. Parts of me get stimulated that I had forgotten I have. Like some kind of abstraction gland. It’s pretty nice.</summary>
    <author>
        <name>tellyou</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<img src="/and/assets/scaled/to/490/wide/and/called/cs61a.png" alt="You see a lecture hall from above. Computer code is projected above the blackboards that contain formulas. The professor stands behind his desk. Many students have computers. To the left one large student wears no shirt." title="" />

<p class="byline"><a href="http://rbmntjs.tumblr.com/post/56407340/check-out-this-douchebag" title="Rob’s brain">Rob notes a shirtless man in CS61A</a></p>

<p>I want to learn how to program. Why, that is for another post. But then where to begin. You can’t just learn programming, it seems, you have to pick one among many of programming languages to learn. And each programming language has a corresponding community. And these communities behave like football supporters for their own language. While they would be better pressed to support programming in general ’cause that’s a cause for which many new converts can still be made, and these converts don’t care for the particularities of your language—yet. Anyway, this turns me off.</p>

<p>So this sounds just right:</p>

<blockquote>In CS 61A, we are interested in teaching you about programming, not about any particular programming language. We consider a series of techniques for controlling program complexity, such as functional programming, data abstraction, object-oriented programming, and query systems. To get past generalities you must have programming practice in some particular language, and in this course we use Scheme, a dialect of Lisp. This language is particularly well-suited to the organizing ideas we want to teach. Our hope, however, is that once you have learned the essence of programming, you will find that picking up a new programming language is but a few days’ work.</blockquote>

<p class="byline"><a href="http://inst.eecs.berkeley.edu/~cs61a/sp11/0.pdf" title="">source</a></p>

<p>I get the <a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/full-text/book/book.html" title="Structure and Interpretation 
of Computer Programs">big blue book</a>, and I start watching the <a href="http://webcast.berkeley.edu/search?cx=005415252586317091923%3Anp2thtbsmyq&amp;cof=FORID%3A10&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=61a&amp;sa=Search&amp;siteurl=webcast.berkeley.edu%2F" title="UC Berkeley Webcasts | Video and Podcasts: Search Courses and Events">screencasts</a>. Parts of me get stimulated that I had forgotten I have. Like some kind of abstraction gland. It’s pretty nice.</p>

<img src="/and/assets/called/sicp_cover.jpg" style="width:400px;height:579px" alt="You see a blue book cover. The title reads, in white: Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs. Over a read background, in black and white, a woodcut of two people engaged in alchemistic practice. Below, the authors read as Harold Abelson and Gerald Jay Sussman, with Julie Sussman" title="" />

<p>But it’s also way too difficult. The way in which Abelson &amp; Sussman explain computation is by consistently comparing it to math. Math is probably a way of thinking in which Science majors are already comfortable. Yet I don’t do math on a regular basis. So it’s like teaching me a language I don’t know by comparing it to another language I don’t really speak either.</p>

<p>A different strategy is needed. I need to work with what I know: words, images. <a href="http://norvig.com/21-days.html" title="Teach Yourself Programming in Ten Years">Peter Norvig says</a> to use whatever your friends are using: “The advantage you get from learning from your friends will offset any intrinsic difference between OS, or between programming languages.” I’m gonna ask my friends to help me get started.</p>

<p>To be continued.</p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>Pattern Recognition</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/pattern-recognition" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2011:/and//1.27</id>

    <published>2011-08-11T00:24:44Z</published>
    <updated>2011-08-11T00:39:16Z</updated>

    <summary>You see the same man twice: In his forties, curly hair, broad, probably Irish descent. The left hand picture sees him en profil, facing right, with his head turned back towards the camera. The other picture is formal, and in black and white. His head turned slightly to the right, the man looks reserved but seemingly content.</summary>
    <author>
        <name>jenseits</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<img src="/and/assets/that/are/screenshots/numbered/0101.png" alt="You see the same man twice: In his forties, curly hair, broad, probably Irish descent. The left hand picture sees him en profil, facing right, with his head turned back towards the camera. He wears a jacket (corduroy?) and a patterned shirt: judging by the colours this photograph is from the 1970ies. The right hand picture is black and white, and looks like it has been taken in the nineteenth century, in a formal sitting. Our subject has turned his head slightly to the right and gazes in the distance, his look reserved but seemingly content." title="" usemap="2john" class="margin-bottom" />
<map name="2john"
<area shape="rect" coords="0,0,340,380" href="http://www.imdb.com/media/rm169246720/nm0000604" title="Pictures & Photos of John C. Reilly - IMDb" />
<area shape="rect" coords="348,0,688,382" href="http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/2006686882/" title="George Henry Boker, 1823-1890, bust, facing left]" />
</map>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>The Fortran Automatic Coding System for the IBM 704</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/the-fortran-automatic-coding-system-for-the-ibm-704" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2011:/and//1.26</id>

    <published>2011-08-03T20:22:42Z</published>
    <updated>2011-08-03T20:37:24Z</updated>

    <summary>You see the front cover to a book, labelled, in bold slab serif letters: Fortran. The cover itself is brown and three holes are pierced through the side</summary>
    <author>
        <name>baseline</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<p><img src="/and/assets/called/fortran_acs_cover.jpg" title="" style="width:610px;height:780px;" alt="You see the front cover to a book, labelled, in bold slab serif letters: Fortran. The cover itself is brown and three holes are pierced through the side." /></p>

<p>This is so beatiful, it is the front cover of the manual for The Fortran Automatic Coding System for the IBM 704, 1956. The typeface is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarendon_(typeface)" title="Clarendon (typeface) - Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia">Clarendon</a>. </p>

<p>IBM’s corporate identity was designed by <a href="http://www.paul-rand.com/site/ibm/" title="Paul-Rand.com :: IBM">Paul Rand</a></p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>Statistical tables</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/statistical-tables" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2011:/and//1.25</id>

    <published>2011-07-28T19:56:12Z</published>
    <updated>2011-07-28T21:48:38Z</updated>

    <summary>You see a picture of a book labelled ‘statistical tables’, positioned on top of a computer mini-tower.</summary>
    <author>
        <name>jenseits</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<img src="/and/assets/scaled/to/830/wide/and/called/IMG_3205.JPG" alt="You see a picture of a book labelled ‘statistical tables’, positioned on top of a computer mini-tower." title="" />]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>Uroboroses</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/uroboroses" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2011:/and//1.24</id>

    <published>2011-07-27T22:48:53Z</published>
    <updated>2011-07-28T20:11:18Z</updated>

    <summary>You see a screenshot of a photo-editing program in which an illustration of an uroboros is manipulated so that all its colors take on a purple hue.</summary>
    <author>
        <name>jenseits</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<a href="/and/assets/that/are/screenshots/numbered/0705.png"><img src="/and/assets/scaled/to/830/wide/that/are/screenshots/numbered/0705.png" alt="You see a screenshot of a photo-editing program in which an illustration of an uroboros is manipulated so that all its colors take on purplue hue." title="" /></a>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>Judging art</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/judging-art" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2011:/and//1.22</id>

    <published>2011-06-07T15:35:15Z</published>
    <updated>2011-07-28T20:28:25Z</updated>

    <summary>I remember the director of Stroom explaining to us, how do we deal with a curator. We should not act too self-assured. Rather, we present an open ended view of our work. Also, we must not expect these curators to make exhibitions with us. We get taught to be subservient</summary>
    <author>
        <name>habitus</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/21128026?portrait=0" width="601" height="338" frameborder="0"></iframe>

<p><a href="http://www.stroom.nl/" title="Stroom Den Haag">Stroom</a> is the local arts body in the city I live in. The city is not very big. To keep cultural live vibrant, the city government tries hard to stimulate the art scene, so that not all artists move to more famous cities. As part of this, for the second time I will be part of <a href="http://www.stroom.nl/paginas/pagina.php?pa_id=9842884" title="Stroom Den Haag - Stroom Invest Programma 2011">a program that introduces artists to curators</a>.</p>

<p>I remember the director of Stroom explaining to us, how do we deal with a curator. We should not act too self-assured. Rather, we present an open ended view of our work. Also, we must not expect these curators to make exhibitions with us. We get taught to be subservient.</p>

<p>Well I'd rather be inquisitive. Once again, I'll spend three days talking to art professionals. I'm not going to try and act spontaneous. This time I'll be keeping notes and I'll share them here. I hope we can answer this question: can the world of contemporary art be fixed?</p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>A New Hymn for Easter</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/a-new-hymn-for-easter" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2011:/and//1.21</id>

    <published>2011-04-25T18:54:37Z</published>
    <updated>2011-07-28T20:31:37Z</updated>

    <summary>To celebrate Easter I translated Gerard Reve&apos;s (1923-2006) ‘Een Nieuw Paaslied’ (1962): “until he entered De Bijenkorf and I, // dizzy with horniness, bumping into people, // lost his trail.”</summary>
    <author>
        <name>glit</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<p>Without having drunk, I praise God.
Today many things happened.<br />
Strolling through the lower city,<br />
thinking of the Final Things,<br />
I saw a boy, presumably a German tourist,<br />
and followed him while I thought:<br />
I'll slap your ass or if that won't work<br />
you can hit me,<br />
the main thing is we're occupied—<br />
until he entered De Bijenkorf and I,<br />
dizzy with horniness, bumping into people,<br />
lost his trail.<br />
Nevertheless I didn't forego praising You.<br />
For unfathomably grand are all your labours:<br />
Thou, who hast made the being<br />
that has a cunt from behind and a tail in front.<br />
Like I said, I hadn't even drunk, and yet I wanted<br />
To honour you weeping and kneel for You in tears,<br />
Oh Master, Slave and Brother, Slaughtered and Risen God.<br />
Humming and secretly prophetising,<br />
I continued on my way.<br />
Then I saw Bet van Beeren, at a little white table<br />
sitting in front of her café, trying with fork and knife<br />
to open up a macrel to eat it in the sun.<br />
I thought look. How beatifully is made everything in Nature.<br />
(Just think about those stars and their lightyears.)<br />
I did want to go to some kind of evening mass,<br />
but there was none.</p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>Illustration</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/illustration" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2011:/and//1.18</id>

    <published>2011-02-20T19:12:06Z</published>
    <updated>2011-07-28T20:33:29Z</updated>

    <summary>You see black and white illustrations of a computer and a penrose triangle, constituted of diagonal contours following a criss cross coarse grid.</summary>
    <author>
        <name>baseline</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<p>
  <object type="image/svg+xml" style="width:900px;height:900px;" data="/and/assets/called/computer.svg">
    <img src="/and/assets/called/computer.png" style="width:900px;height:900px;" alt="A stylised image of a computer displaying a window manager. The image is constituted of diagonal contours following a criss cross coarse grid." />
  </object>
</p>
<p>
  <object type="image/svg+xml" style="width:900px;height:900px;" data="/and/assets/called/triangle.svg">
    <img src="/and/assets/called/triangle.png" style="width:900px;height:900px;" alt="A stylised image of a penrose triangle. The image is constituted of diagonal contours following a criss cross coarse grid." />
  </object>
</p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>Beta</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/beta" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2010:/and//1.16</id>

    <published>2010-09-04T22:15:37Z</published>
    <updated>2011-07-28T20:36:37Z</updated>

    <summary>You see a number of GIF illustrations from the 1990ies. Apparently there are people who can develop, design and write it all at the same time. I can not. That’s why it’s BETA. But luckily I am working with Rowan now.</summary>
    <author>
        <name>baseline</name>
        
    </author>
    
    <category term="beta" label="beta" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#tag" />
    <category term="collaboration" label="collaboration" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#tag" />
    <category term="construction" label="construction" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#tag" />
    <category term="design" label="design" scheme="http://www.sixapart.com/ns/types#tag" />
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<p>
<img src="/and/assets/called/AIconsWwwConst_anim.gif" style="width:38px;height:38px;" alt="AIconsWwwConst Anim" />
<img src="/and/assets/called/AIconsWwwConst_area.png" style="width:78px;height:53px;" alt="AIconsWwwConst Area" />
<img src="/and/assets/called/AIconsWwwConst_barrier.png" style="width:39px;height:35px;" alt="AIconsWwwConst Barrier" />
<img src="/and/assets/called/AIconsWwwConst_build.png" style="width:64px;height:38px;" alt="AIconsWwwConst Build" />
<img src="/and/assets/called/AIconsWwwConst_gear.gif" style="width:93px;height:70px;" alt="AIconsWwwConst Gear" />
<img src="/and/assets/called/AIconsWwwConst_hat.png" style="width:32px;height:32px;" alt="AIconsWwwConst Hat" />
<img src="/and/assets/called/AIconsWwwConst_hole.png" style="width:144px;height:50px;" alt="AIconsWwwConst Hole" />
<img src="/and/assets/called/AIconsWwwConst_landscape.gif" style="width:249px;height:87px;" alt="AIconsWwwConst Landscape" />
<img src="/and/assets/called/AIconsWwwConst_sign.gif" style="width:246px;height:63px;" alt="AIconsWwwConst Sign" />
<img src="/and/assets/called/AIconsWwwConst_under.png" style="width:125px;height:39px;" alt="AIconsWwwConst Under" />
<img src="/and/assets/called/AIconsWwwConst_warn.png" style="width:49px;height:43px;" alt="AIconsWwwConst Warn" />
<img src="/and/assets/called/AIconsWwwConstruction.png" style="width:40px;height:40px;" alt="AIconsWwwConstruction" />
</p>

<p>Reading yet <a href="http://blog.peepcode.com/tutorials/2010/about-this-blog" title="About this Blog | Free PeepCode Blog">another programming blog with great design</a>, I feel ashamed for the shape this site is in.</p>

<p>Well, it is in beta! Apparently there are people who can pull it off, but I think my website will be better if I do not develop, design and write it all at the same time.</p>

<p>For the visual identity I am now working with <a href="http://www.mccuskey.nl/" title="Jij &amp; McCuskey">Rowan</a>. I am sure it will turn out wonderful. Stay tuned.</p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>Honest artist statements</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/honest-artist-statements" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2010:/and//1.12</id>

    <published>2010-07-09T16:15:35Z</published>
    <updated>2011-07-28T20:37:22Z</updated>

    <summary>I keep changing around this text. Because I do not know who you are I get no clues as to what I should talk about. I talk in abstractions of meaning, art and revolution.</summary>
    <author>
        <name>tellyou</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<p><em>An artist statement is a text you write when you apply for a scholarship or open call, and that you keep around on your website.</em></p>

<p>I keep changing around this text. Because I do not know who you are I get no clues as to what I should talk about. I talk in abstractions of meaning, art and revolution.</p> 

<p>You of course stay silent.</p>

<p>I try harder to convince you that my thoughts are interesting and that you should say something back. I even try to convince you that I understand everything.</p>

<p>This, at times is true, and then I always think I must be interesting to talk to. Yet understanding in itself does not amount to much.</p>

<p>Sense we can only make inbetween the both of us.</p>

<p>What I think I am actually saying is: I would like you to talk to me. That would be good. You can call or mail me, and we will meet and talk. Or just look out of the window together, which is even better.</p>

<p>There is a second message. Which is: let us mount shows with my pictures. I would like that.</p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>Talking of content</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/talking-of-content" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2010:/and//1.11</id>

    <published>2010-06-08T21:05:38Z</published>
    <updated>2011-07-28T20:39:27Z</updated>

    <summary>My strongest first impression was the sense of confrontation that was instigated, not in the content per se but as evident from the two questions (…). The stance is important, and even political. It reminds me of feminism. And I suppose its the direct reply to that “geeky” fear we have.</summary>
    <author>
        <name>jenseits</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/12366245?byline=0&amp;portrait=0&amp;color=7C26FF" width="830" height="436" frameborder="0"></iframe><p class="byline"><a href="http://vimeo.com/12366245">Content centric architecture and distributed versioning</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/seeculture">See Culture</a> on <a href="http://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</p>

<p>At the <a href="http://libregraphicsmeeting.org/2010/">Libre Graphics Meeting</a>, a four day event bringing together open source developers and graphic professionals.</p>

<p>Correction @ 4:52: the <a href="http://klepas.org/openbaskerville/" title="Open Baskerville">Open Baskerville</a> project has been initiated by <a href="http://klepas.org/" title="Simon Pascal Klein&thinsp;&mdash;&thinsp;Graphic &amp; web design professional">Simon Pascal Klein</a> from Australia (not Pascal Simon Klein from Germany). Apologies!</p>

<p>Video originally on <a href="http://river-valley.tv/content-centric-architecture-and-distributed-versioning/">http://river-valley.tv/content-centric-architecture-and-distributed-versioning/</a></p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

<entry>
    <title>The problem with web apps</title>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/the-problem-with-web-apps" />
    <id>tag:i.liketightpants.net,2010:/and//1.8</id>

    <published>2010-04-07T18:10:09Z</published>
    <updated>2011-07-28T21:05:16Z</updated>

    <summary>Apps become like this:&apos; a circle labelled APP encapsulating a circle labelled DATA. The app interfaces with a square with rounded corners labeled USER, as shown by two way arrows. &apos;While potentially they could be:&apos; the user interfaces with a circle APP which interfaces with a separate circle DATA. &apos;The latter could enable&apos;: the USER interfaces with an APP which interfaces with an APP which interfaces with an APP which interfaces with DATA. &apos;As well as:&apos; the USER interfaces with three APPS that all interface with DATA. &apos;(Or any combination of the two)&apos;</summary>
    <author>
        <name>jenseits</name>
        
    </author>
    
    
    <content type="html" xml:lang="en" xml:base="http://i.liketightpants.net/and/">
        <![CDATA[<p>
  <object type="image/svg+xml" style="width:830px;height:992px;" data="/and/assets/called/theproblemwithwebapps.svg">
    <img src="/and/assets/called/theproblemwithwebapps.png" style="width:736px;height:880px;" alt="'Apps become like this:' a circle labelled APP encapsulating a circle labelled DATA. The app interfaces with a square with rounded corners labeled USER, as shown by two way arrows. 'While potentially they could be:' the user interfaces with a circle APP which interfaces with a separate circle DATA. 'The latter could enable': the USER interfaces with an APP which interfaces with an APP which interfaces with an APP which interfaces with DATA. 'As well as:' the USER interfaces with three APPS that all interface with DATA. '(Or any combination of the two)' " />
  </object>
</p>

<p>Applied to blogging software:</p>

<p><img src="/and/assets/called/fromacontentperspective.png" style="width:600px;height:1615px;"></p>]]>
        
    </content>
</entry>

</feed>

